[Music]
Now
another
digression in order to exercise our
dimensional imagination and stretch our
intuition a little bit. This um
digression is not necessary for the
remainder of the course. So you can fall
asleep if you like. But if you're awake,
you'll see something again rather weird.
Let's ask ourselves what is the volume
of
the m dimensional ball. What's the
radius of this?
Do you remember from yesterday when I
defined it? What's the radius of this
ball? One. One. Always unit ball.
[Applause]
Okay. So, what's the volume of the ball
in dimension M? A unit ball in dimension
M. Now, in dimension one,
we know that
we don't talk about volume. Instead, we
talk about length.
And in dimension
two, volume really means area as you can
imagine. But scientists are lazy people.
They don't want to be talking about
different words all the time. So we talk
about volume all the time. Okay. Now we
know some data dimension M and volume of
BM in dimension 1 2 3. We surely know
what's the volume of the one-dimensional
ball. One ball.
Nope. Two. Because the one dimensional
ball is the set of all the points that
are within distance one from the origin.
So it's from minus1 to one. The length
of that is two not one. So it is two.
Okay. And what's the volume of the two
dimensional ball? Two ball
unit radius. Who said pi again? Well
looked at pi. And how about the volume
of the threedimensional ball?
Huh? You all know this.
What do you think?
What's the No, no, no. What? What do you
think? The d the volume of the
threedimensional ball. Huh? Do you have
Do you remember learning a formula
somewhere in your life? What was it?
Say something so that you can make a
mistake.
Say something.
Say anything.
3 pi over 4. Okay.
Is this right?
It's not
4 pi over 3. But it's not too far away.
Okay. So now, but now now you know. Now
you know.
Yeah. Because you made a mistake. Now
you know. It was a good opportunity to
revise. So you should say something. Why
is three downstairs? Because that's the
result of integrating
from dimension two to dimension three.
When you integrate, you have to divide
by the exponent. And that's why three is
downstairs. 4 pi is the area of the unit
sphere. And that's related. Okay. And
now we'd like to see what the
the volumes of these balls are in all
dimensions. Okay. I shall not do this
calculation. Okay? But I'll state the
result and it will be a very good piece
of mathematical education if you looked
it up somewhere and if you cannot look
it up I'll be happy to help you. It's a
wonderful beautiful exercise in
integration to show that volume of the
unit
ball is equal to p<unk> ^ m / 2 over m /
factorial.
Now because you attentive you are going
to complain immediately. For example,
Dina was going to complain this
factorial does not make sense because
when m is even I know what the factorial
of an integer is. Suppose m is three.
What does 3 /2 factorial mean? You are
going to complain, right? Thank you very
much for complaining. And
in order to define the factorial for non
integer values, factorial of non-
integer number, we have to introduce
the gamma function. Now gamma function
for historical reasons, it's due to
ljan. This notation is shifted by one
with respect to the factorial. That's a
shame and I wish that we could just
start using this notation all over the
world but it's too late. All the books
and all the professors have learned it
this way and we cannot go back. But
anyway, so this gamma function
fn looks means gamma function is the
laplas transform if you like of s and
then e to um sorry e minus x uh s x and
dx. That's right.
Okay.
So for
radius
r recall that the we are talking about
the unit radius but for radius r just
multiply
by what factor in dimension m
r2
a. If you make this ball have radius R
rather than radius one, we have to
multiply this answer by what factor.
R2.
R2 is an exponent m. That's right.
Because that's what the volume. So for
example in threedimensional space you
have to multiply it by r cubed. Okay.
Okay.
Now the funny thing about this answer is
the following.
Oh, before we state the funny thing,
let's find out if this is correct. So
when m is one, is this going to give
two? Really,
in order to understand this, we have to
know something about what minus half
factorial is which is equal to gamma of
12. This turns out to be it's the
Gaussian integral turns out to be pi
square to pi. And then there's a
recurrence formula which says that gamma
of s + 1 equals s * gamma of s. So these
two allow you to calculate the gamma
function for all half integers. And it
turns out that if you do the check all
those numbers come up. Okay. And so
please maybe look up if you're
interested. Again this is not part of
the course. So it's not discuss but if
you're interested please look up the
theory of gamma functions. It's easy and
find out what the volume of a unit ball
is in 4D. It will be interesting.
However, we don't have to know the exact
values of the gamma functions in order
to say the following thing.
You see that the there's an exponential
upstairs exponential in m downstairs in
the numerator there's a factorial.
Which grows faster exponential or
factorial?
There are some people who say
exponential. There are some people who
say factorial. Factorial grows much
faster than exponential.
Do you have this kind of sense? This
kind of sense of orders of growth is
very important in applications of
mathematics all over science. So you say
that any polomial grows faster than
logarithm
any power function. Yeah. And any
exponential grows faster than polinomial
power functions. And any factorial goes
faster than
exponential. So since factorial
grows faster than exponential.
As you take the limit of higher and
higher dimension,
the volume of the unit ball in those
dimensions
rapidly converges to zero.
In other words, in high dimensions,
balls are extremely small.
Again, really interesting phenomenon of
high dimensional spaces. Okay.
You are certainly wondering what the
volume or the surface area of the sphere
is. So to find the volume of SM minus
one,
you can just differentiate
the volume
of um M ball
of radius
R
and put
R = 1.
Okay.
And the result
state
I'll state it so that you have something
to look at later on.
In case you're taking notes,
so the volume of s mus1 is equal to<unk>
of m / 2 / m / 2 -1
factorial. In terms of gamma functions,
you might look a little cleaner, but
that's what it is. Okay,
good.
Any questions so far? This was the
operation number one, products. What's
important for the rest of the course is
really the first half of this
discussion. This um discussion of the
middle ball sticking out and volumes of
higher dimensional balls. That's for
your general culture. That's for our
general culture. Okay, let's go on to
then operation number two.
This is the concept of quotient. In
other words, instead of multiplying, we
are beginning to divide. In some sense,
quotient is a very common and rather
universal concept in mathematics. You
might have learned about co quotient
set, quotient space. When you have an
equivalence relationship in a in a set,
that's more what we mean. But we shall
do everything in terms of pictures
again. So example seven will give you a
good idea.
Let's start from a unit square.
So that's I2.
I mean all this. And now I shall
introduce this funny symbol. On this
edge I'm going to put this arrow. On
this edge I'm going to put this arrow.
on the remaining two edges I put
nothing.
Now if you see a picture like this it
means please take this edge which has
arrow and take the other edge which has
arrow and identify or glue together
those two edges and do nothing else.
Okay. So what does this mean? It means
the following.
I'm drawing the arrow down because it's
the so-called projection map for the
quotient set. But you don't have to
worry about this. So what we do is
identify
the two vertical edges
in this case left and right. And what we
do is you can imagine right if you think
of this as made of paper and you
identify the edges you get this kind of
picture.
Agreed?
You covered it but that's okay. We are
doing topology. So and then this
boundary this part of the boundary
disappeared because now
this part and this part have been glued.
The top and bottom boundaries are still
there. So what we find is the result is
a cylinder
and what is a cylinder? It is S1 cross
I. So I took this quotient we say of I2
and I end up with S1 cross I. S1
component is this component and I
component is the vertical component.
Okay.
So we write this it's just a matter of
terminology but we
this operation
as I2 the original square where we
divide this or take the quotient of this
by an equivalence relation. What is the
equivalence relation we're using? It is
simply equal to saying that all points
of the form of the coordinates 0 y is
identified with points of the
coordinates one y for all y.
What do I mean? Well, if I think of this
corner as the origin, this is point one
from the origin. This point one
vertically from the origin.
This point for example would have
coordinates y x coordinate is zero and
some y coordinate. This point should be
identified with this point.
What is the what are the coordinates of
this point? It is one and y. So those
two must be identified which is
represented by this symbol.
Don't tell me you don't understand. It's
very very simple. Of course you
understand.
You agree that this operation means that
this point must be identified with this
point. This point must be identified
with this point. This point is the same
point as this point. This point is the
same point as this point. Yeah, that's
what gluing means. Okay, so if this is
the inside XY coordinate planes,
let's see what the coordinates of this
point are. Yeah, this height is less Y.
Well, this point has coordinates. What
are the coordinates?
0 Y. What are the coordinates of this
point? The same height one Y. So this
point must be the same. And that's
exactly what I'm right. So you see, you
shake your head in desperation and
tragic tragic appearance. But in fact
it's very easy. That's what mathematics
is. Okay. So that's what we write and we
say that as a result of this
division if you like we get
that.
Okay.
Okay. So, and so we say
we write it like that and say that
the cylinder
is the quotient
of the square
by the given equivalence class or the
equivalence relation if you like or more
commonly identification.
So that's what the quotient space is.
Simply you take some manifold and then
you take some part and you take some
other part and you just glue them
together and then you create a new
geometric figure and that's the
operation of quotient that corresponds
to division if you like. Okay, let's see
a few other examples of quotient
of the quotient.
What we have created above you see is
what do you might call the ordinary
strip because I took a rectangle square
is the same thing topologically and then
glued like this. What's the next natural
thing to do? Instead of gluing them like
this, let's twist one side and glue
That's a familiar friend.
Movie strip.
How do we represent a movie strip in
terms of this arrow diagram?
Well,
quite easy.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I hear you. So you
take again the unit square.
This time I put an arrow like this, but
I put a downward arrow like this. That's
all you do. And then what you end up
seeing is that well it's probably easier
to see it this way
first.
Let's see it this way. So, I bent it
over,
but here up and down are the opposite.
So, in order to glue them, I have to do
something to one of them. So, let's
twist one
and we get this picture. Both arrows
pointing up. Now, we are ready to glue
them. They're in the same orientation.
So we can identify point point and then
the resulting surface is an old friend
as we noticed before it is none other
than the movie strip that we played
with. So mer on the first day.
Oops.
Movie strip with one twist.
Movie strip with two twists
topologically speaking is the same thing
as that cylinder. Although in R3 it
might be positioned in a different way.
That's a story for later on. So what
this is in terms of that notation is
somewhat diff. So this time you identify
zero y
with one. What do you think?
Not minus one almost.
For example, if y is 0.1,
I want to identify it with the point
0.9.
If y is 0.2, I want to identify it with
the point the
one one minus y. That's correct. So all
this and that sort of reverses
orientation and glues that's the twist
mathematically speaking or the
symbolically this is what twist is. And
so this is the movie strip that you get.
Okay, you see that we are not doing
mathematics. We're doing uh linguistics
in some sense. It's we are learning just
new language and new notation. But these
things will be very useful to manipulate
later on when we do real mathematics.
Okay. Next example nine. Again we shall
meet an old friend. Let's start
identifying not only the vertical edges
but also the horizontals.
First the simplest to visualize is
vertically I glue straight horizontally
I also glue straight. What is this going
to become?
First let's glue the verticals. Then
it's easy. In fact it's result is
exactly the same as in example seven.
You get a cylinder.
The difference this time is that it's
not the end of this identification. We
still have to do the identification
of the top circle to the bottom circle.
Now, how do we represent this? Here's
what how I would like to think about.
I'm going to bend this cylinder like
this.
Bless you.
By the way, you know that in English
somebody sneezes and you're supposed to
say bless you. Do you have that kind of
expression in your languages, in your
culture? In French, there's an
interesting habit. So when somebody
sneezes, you say to your wishes. When
somebody sneezes twice in a row, you say
aamu to your loves.
Plural. And when somebody sneezes three
times, you say to your children.
Okay? So you still have to identify
those two. And it's be you see what you
can think of it this way. You have this
tube and then I took this and brought it
down. And so this circle is going like
this. This circle when it comes down is
going round like this. And when you
identify
you get I'm sorry I'm going to suddenly
draw a smaller Taurus but you get of
course a Taurus.
Okay. So again, so this is the
identification
of vertical edges
and this projection is the
identification of horizontal edges
or horizontal circles if you like.
Okay, so we can do a lot of different
things and it doesn't matter which sort
of horizontal or vertical you identify
first and the symbolic representation
should be completely familiar to you by
now. The first bit of identification is
as before. So that's no problem. 0 y and
1 y should be identified. So that's the
vertical edge identification for all y.
What about the horizontal
identification? So I want to identify
this point with this point, this point
with this point, this point with this
point and so on. So what are the
identifications?
X0. Thank you. And
X1 correct. So that's the
identification. And the result is of
course Taurus T2,
not Tashi this time. Okay.
Are you all um
happy about this? Now let me draw a
strange picture
and then we shall take a break.
What happens if I take that Taurus and
please note that this Taurus is drawn
vertically. So earlier we tried to
visualize
a donut Taurus which is horizontal be
but now we are visualizing it
vertically. It doesn't matter which one.
This Taurus has a plane of symmetry as
we like to call it. This plane this half
and this half are completely the same.
Mirror images of each other. If you cut
it like this it's also the same but I'd
like to cut it like this. Okay.
So, so the resulting thing will be this
half and this half. If I cut it like
this, then you divide it into top and
bottom. But I'm cutting it like this.
What happens if you cut it vertically?
Well, it's not too difficult to imagine.
What happens is that we share this donut
between me and somebody else.
And
here is
what do we get
if we slice
this Taurus
in half or halves? Do you know the
plural of half? One half, two halves.
It's not halves.
So the picture is as follows. You have a
Taurus and then you're about to cut it
about share this donut. It is a rather
giant donut. So if I slice it in this
plane of symmetry, what you get is the
following picture.
And I'll try to draw as realistic a
picture as I I can manage. You get some
picture like this. So let me shade this.
So this was the part that used to be
outside and this is still entirely on
the outside.
Yeah, there's something strange sticking
out but that comes from the cut from the
other side. Now if you think about it,
each one of one of these
is simply equal to
this angulus.
And so we can also represent it as
by the following picture.
Ordinary strip
together with
another ordinary strip. Now, you might
think that this is a somewhat
complicated way of saying this a simple
thing, but we'll see why it's
interesting when we cut something else
other than the Taurus. But anyway, you
have two copies
of what we called on the first day
ordinary strip.
But we now have
an official name. It is S1 cross I. If
you see what it is, I mean it's short
this way and very long this way over
there and in example seven or over here
example seven it's long this way short
this way but it's topologically the same
thing.
Okay.
So I'm going to ask a question and then
we take a five minute break and then we
shall continue.
I'm erasing this monstrous example of
the 10 dimensional sphere packing. Okay,
example 10.
I'd like to ask you what is this?
That's really strange, huh?
I didn't make a mistake. I'm taking this
edge and identifying it with this edge
and this edge identifying with this
edge. Can you guess what's going to
happen
topologically?
So I get rid of all the edges. So there
will be no boundary at the end. I'm
taking this if you think of this as made
of elastic material. And then I take
this and close. I take these and close.
What do you get? You get something like
a pouch, a bag, mathematically, it's
just S2, two dimensional space.
Where are we going? You see, whenever
you have a square diagram, you can
identify the edges in many many
different ways, but there are only
finitely many possibilities.
So, let's discover all the possibilities
and what happens. So far, we have done
several possibilities. For example,
that's one possibility. Only two edges
identified and some of these have four
edges identified. But there are some
other possibilities. For example, I can
identify this edge with this edge like
this and these two edges like this. Then
what's going to happen? And so let's
take a break for five minutes and we
shall continue.